<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.4/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.4/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.4.xsd" version="0.4" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.16wmf4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ford Mustang</title>
    <id>105908</id>
    <revision>
      <id>369712226</id>
      <timestamp>2010-06-23T09:57:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Luckas-bot</username>
        <id>7320905</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>robot Adding: [[hi:फोर्ड मस्टैंग (Ford Mustang)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Automobile
| image = [[Image:2011 Ford Mustang v6 Coupe.jpg|250px|2011 Ford Mustang V6 Coupe]] ''2011 Ford Mustang''
| name = Ford Mustang
| manufacturer = [[Ford Motor Company]]
| parent_company =
| aka =
| production = 1964 – present
| assembly = [[United States]]
| predecessor =
| successor =
| class = [[Pony car]]
| body_style = 2-door [[2+2 (car body style)|2+2]] seat [[coupé]]&lt;br&gt;2-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br&gt;2-door [[convertible]]
| layout = [[FR layout]]
}}

[[Image:Ford mustang badge.jpg|frame|2010 model Ford Mustang badge]]

The '''Ford Mustang''' is an [[automobile]] manufactured car by the [[Ford Motor Company]]. It was initially based on the second generation North American [[Ford Falcon (North America)|Ford Falcon]], a [[compact car]].&lt;ref&gt;''Iacocca: An Autobiography'', by [[Lee Iacocca]], Chapter VI&lt;/ref&gt; Introduced early on April 17, 1964,&lt;ref&gt;Flory, J. &quot;Kelly&quot;, Jr. ''American Cars 1960–1972'' (Jefferson, NC: McFarland &amp; Coy, 2004), p.367.&lt;/ref&gt; the 1965 Mustang is the automaker's most successful launch since the [[Ford Model A (1927–1931)|Model A]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last = Hinckley|first = Jim|last2 = Robinson|first2 = Jon G.|title = The Big Book of Car Culture|publisher = MotorBooks/MBI|year = 2005|page = 175|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=NorSiqCb9mMC&amp;pg=PA175&amp;dq=%22most+successful+introduction%22+automobile&amp;lr=&amp;ei=5kGmSKmLCJjgiQGCqqH6BA&amp;sig=ACfU3U1BMvIzvInczLVKp9fAChwP0wkw3w|isbn = 9780760319659 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Mustang created the &quot;[[pony car]]&quot; class of American automobile — sports car-like [[coupe]]s with long hoods and short rear decks&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last = Mueller|first = Mike|title = Ford Mustang|publisher = MotorBooks/MBI|year = 1997|page = 21|isbn = 9780879389901 }}&lt;/ref&gt; — and gave rise to competitors such as GM's [[Chevrolet Camaro]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last = Young|first = Anthony|title = Camaro|publisher = MotorBooks/MBI|year = 2004 |page = 8|isbn = 9780760319321 }}&lt;/ref&gt; AMC's [[AMC Javelin|Javelin]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title = Dick Teague|journal = Automobile Quarterly, Volume 30 |issue = 2|page = 15|year = 1992 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Chrysler's revamped [[Plymouth Barracuda]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last = Zazarine|first = Paul|title = Barracuda and Challenger|publisher = MotorBooks/MBI|year = 2002|page = 29|isbn = 9780879385385}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also inspired coupés such as the [[Toyota Celica]] and [[Ford Capri]], which were exported to America.

==Background==

Production of the 1965 Mustang began in [[Dearborn, Michigan]] on March 9, 1964 and the car was introduced to the public on April 17, 1964 at the [[1964 New York World's Fair|New York World's Fair]]. It is Ford's third oldest nameplate currently in production next to the [[Ford F-Series|F-Series]] pickup truck line (which has undergone major nameplate changes over the years) and the [[Ford Falcon (Australia)|Falcon]] which is still in production in [[Australia]].

Executive stylist Pres Harris, who was a fan of the World War II [[P-51 Mustang]] fighter plane, is believed by many to have suggested the name and designed the body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.allfordmustangs.com/articles/Ford_Mustang_I_Prototype_Failed_Appeal_to_the_Crowds.shtml &quot;Ford Mustang Prototype Failed to Appeal to the Crowds&quot;, ''All Ford Mustang News'' website, May 03 2008]. Retrieved on August 25, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fordpr&gt;[http://media.ford.com/article_display.cfm?article_id=18000 “Mustang Racing History”, Ford Corporate Media website]. Retrieved on August 25, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; An alternative view was that the Mustang name was first suggested by Robert J. Eggert, Ford Division market research manager. Eggert, a breeder of [[quarterhorses]], received a birthday present from his wife of the book, ''The Mustangs'' by [[J. Frank Dobie]] in 1960. Later, the book’s title gave him the idea of adding the “Mustang” name for Ford’s new concept car. The designer preferred Cougar or [[Turin|Torino]] (and an advertising campaign using the Torino name was actually prepared), while [[Henry Ford II]] wanted T-bird II.&lt;ref&gt;Witzenburg, Gary. &quot;The Name Game&quot;, ''Motor Trend'', 4/84, p.86.&lt;/ref&gt; As the person responsible for Ford’s research on potential names, Eggert added “Mustang” to the list to be tested by focus groups; “Mustang,” by a wide margin, ” came out on top under the heading: “Suitability as Name for the Special Car.”&lt;ref&gt;Walter T. Murphy, &quot;Toot Toot: The Life of a PR Man,&quot; (Birmingham, Michigan, Walmur Publishing 1984), page 125.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James Eggert, &quot;Meadowlark Economics: Collected Essays,&quot; (Berkeley, California, North Atlantic Books, 2009), page 65-66.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kate Pierce, &quot;Name That Car,&quot; (Automotive, May 26, 1994), page C.&lt;/ref&gt; The name could not be used in Germany,&lt;ref&gt;Witzenburg, p.86.&lt;/ref&gt; however, because it was owned by [[Krupp]], which had manufactured trucks between 1951 and 1964 with the name Mustang.  Ford refused to buy the name for about $10,000 [[United States dollar|USD]] from [[Krupp]] at the time.  Later, the name was also used by [[Kreidler]], a manufacturer of mopeds, so until December 1978 the Mustang was sold in Germany as the &quot;T-5.&quot;

Mustangs grew larger and heavier with each model year until, in response to the 1971–1973 models, fans of the original 1964 design wrote to Ford urging a return to its size and concept. It has since seen several platform generations and designs. Although some other pony cars have seen a revival, the Mustang is the only original pony car to remain in uninterrupted production over four decades of development and revision.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.ford.com/NEWSROOM/feature_display.cfm?release=24065N Mustang Ready For the Pony Car War &quot;Mustang is the only one of the original pony cars from the 1960s to live on into the 21st century with no interruption in production.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== First generation (1964½–1973) ==
{{main|Ford Mustang (first generation)}}

[[File:1964-mustang-rc.jpg|thumb|right|1964½ Mustang]]

As [[Lee Iacocca]]'s assistant general manager and chief engineer, [[Donald N. Frey]] was the head engineer for the Mustang project—supervising the overall development of the Mustang in a record 18 months&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetech.org/nmot/detail.cfm?ID=8&amp; &quot;Donald N. Frey, lauteate 1990&quot; National Medal of Technology], retrieved on August 16, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,843628,00.html &quot;The Thinker (Detroit Style)&quot; Time magazine, April 21, 1967], retrieved on August 16, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; — while Iacocca himself championed the project as Ford Division general manager. The Mustang prototype was a two-seat, mid-mounted engine [[roadster]]. This vehicle employed a Taunus (Ford Germany) V4 engine and was very similar in appearance to the much later [[Pontiac Fiero]].

It was claimed that the decision to abandon the two-seat design was in part due to the low sales experienced with the 2-seat 1955 Thunderbird. To broaden market appeal it was later remodeled as a four-seat car (with full space for the front bucket seats, as originally planned, and a rear bench seat with significantly less space than was common at the time). A &quot;Fastback 2+2&quot; model traded the conventional trunkspace for increased interior volume as well as giving exterior lines similar to those of the second series of the Corvette Sting Ray and European sports cars such as the [[Jaguar E-Type]].

The new design was styled under the direction of Project Design Chief [[Joe Oros]] and his team of [[L. David Ash]], Gale Halderman, and John Foster&lt;ref name=&quot;midco&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = 1962 Mustang Designed by David Ashf
| publisher = Midcomustang.com
| url = http://www.midcomustang.com/daveash.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/11/garden/11viktor.html?ex=1176177600&amp;en=70832a56ef031791&amp;ei=5070 | last = Rohrlich | first = Marianne | title = Belatedly, Stardom Finds a 20th-Century Master |  newspaper = The New York Times | date = 2006-05-11 | accessdate = 2010-05-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; — in Ford's [[Lincoln (automobile)|Lincoln]] – [[Mercury (automobile)|Mercury]] Division design studios, which produced the winning design in an intramural design contest instigated by Iacocca.

Having set the design standards for the Mustang,&lt;ref name=&quot;DMN&quot;&gt;{{Citation | title = Fans celebrate Mustang's 40th | newspaper = Dallas Morning News | url = http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/autos/topstories2/041604ccAutosMustangparty.12fe23361.html | date = 2004-04-16 | last = Reeves | first = Scott  | accessdate = 2010-05-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Oros said:

{{cquote|I told the team that I wanted the car to appeal to women, but I wanted men to desire it, too. I wanted a Ferrari-like front end, the motif centered on the front – something heavy-looking like a Maserati, but, please, not a trident – and I wanted air intakes on the side to cool the rear brakes. I said it should be as sporty as possible and look like it was related to European design.&lt;ref name=&quot;DMN&quot; /&gt;}}

Oros added:

{{cquote|I then called a meeting with all the Ford studio designers. We talked about the sporty car for most of that afternoon, setting parameters for what it should look like—and what it should not look like—by making lists on a large pad, a technique I adapted from the management seminar. We taped the lists up all around the studio to keep ourselves on track. We also had photographs of all the previous sporty cars that had been done in the Corporate Advanced studio as a guide to themes or ideas that were tired or not acceptable to management.

Within a week we had hammered out a new design. We cut templates and fitted them to the clay model that had been started. We cut right into it, adding or deleting clay to accommodate our new theme, so it wasn't like starting all over. But we knew Lincoln-Mercury would have two models. And Advanced would have five, some they had previously shown and modified, plus a couple extras. But we would only have one model because Ford studio had a production schedule for a good many facelifts and other projects. We couldn't afford the manpower, but we made up for lost time by working around the clock so our model would be ready for the management review.&lt;ref name=&quot;midco&quot; /&gt;}}

Favorable [[publicity]] articles appeared in 2,600 newspapers the next morning, the day the car was &quot;officially&quot; revealed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://auto.howstuffworks.com/1965-1966-ford-mustang.htm &quot;1965 1966 Ford Mustang,&quot; by the Auto Editors of ''Consumer Guide'', February 4, 2007], retrieved on August 16, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.ford.com/article_display.cfm?article_id=18037 Innovative Marketing and PR Helped Build the Mustang Legend by Ford Motor Company Media, undated], retrieved on August 16, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; A Mustang also appeared in the James Bond film ''[[Goldfinger (film)|Goldfinger]]'' in September 1964, the first time the car was used in a movie.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mi6.co.uk/sections/articles/collecting_nikko_goldfinger.php3 &quot;Carrera Goldfinger Racing Set Review&quot; ''MI6'', August 26, 2005], retrieved on August 8, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

To cut down the development cost and achieve a [[suggested retail price]] of [[United States dollar|US$]]2,368, the Mustang was based heavily on familiar yet simple components, many of which were already in production for other Ford models. Many (if not most) of the interior, [[chassis]], [[suspension (vehicle)|suspension]], and drivetrain components were derived from the [[Ford Falcon (North American)|Ford Falcon]] and [[Ford Fairlane (North American)]]. This use of common components also shortened the learning curve for assembly and repair workers, while at the same time allowing dealers to pick up the Mustang without also have to spend massive amounts of money on spare parts inventories to support the new car line.

Original sales forecasts projected less than 100,000 units for the first year.&lt;ref name=&quot;google30&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last = Mueller|first = Mike|title = Mustang 1964½-1973|publisher = MotorBooks/MBI|year = 2000|page = 30|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=12Unsmyljk4C&amp;pg=PA30&amp;dq=Mustang+sales+first+year&amp;lr=&amp;ei=n0amSP7XFpD0jgHx87D7BA&amp;sig=ACfU3U1s9XLMW2tPSCsGGnYWetWWmFNYfg#PPA30,M1|isbn = 9780760307342 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This mark was surpassed in three months from rollout.&lt;ref&gt;Flory, pp. 367–8.&lt;/ref&gt; Another 318,000 would be sold during the model year (a record),&lt;ref&gt;Flory, p. 368.&lt;/ref&gt; and in its first eighteen months, more than one million Mustangs were built.&lt;ref name=&quot;google30&quot; /&gt; All of these were [[Vehicle Identification Number|VIN]]-identified as 1965 models, but several changes were made at the traditional opening of the new model year (beginning August 1964), including the addition of back-up lights on some models, the introduction of [[Alternator#Automotive alternators|alternators]] to replace [[Electrical generator#Vehicle-mounted generators|generator]]s, and an upgrade of the V8 engine from {{convert|260|cid|l|1|abbr=on}} to {{convert|289|cid|l|1|abbr=on}} [[engine displacement|displacement]]. In the case of at least some six-cylinder Mustangs fitted with the {{convert|101|hp|kW|abbr=on}} {{convert|170|cid|l|1|abbr=on}} Falcon engine, the rush into production included some unusual quirks, such as a horn ring bearing the 'Ford Falcon' logo beneath a trim ring emblazoned with 'Ford Mustang.' These characteristics made enough difference to warrant designation of the 121,538 earlier ones as &quot;1964½&quot; model-year Mustangs, a distinction that has endured with purists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theautochannel.com/news/2009/04/16/457244.html |title=The Great Mustang Debate: 1964 or 1965 |publisher=Theautochannel.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;'''

All of the features added to the &quot;1965&quot; model were available as options or developmental modification to the &quot;1964½&quot; model, which in some cases led to &quot;mix-and-match&quot; confusion as surprised Ford exec hurriedly ramped up production by taking over lines originally intended for other car models' 1965 years. Some cars with 289 engines which were not given the chrome fender badges denoting the larger engine, and more than one car left the plant with cutouts for back-up lights but no lights nor the later wiring harness needed to operate them. While these would today be additional-value collectors' items, most of these oddities were corrected at the dealer level, sometimes only after they had been noticed by buyers.

== Second generation (1974–1978) ==
{{main|Ford Mustang (second generation)}}
[[Image:Ford Mustang II.jpg|thumb|1974–1978 Mustang II.]]

The 1970s brought about more stringent pollution laws and the [[1973 OPEC oil embargo]]. As a result, large, fuel-inefficient cars fell into disfavor, and the Pony Cars were no exception. [[Lee Iacocca]], who became president of the Ford Motor Company in 1964 and was the driving force behind the original Mustang, ordered a smaller, more fuel-efficient Mustang for 1974. Initially it was to be based on the [[Ford Maverick (Car)|Ford Maverick]], but ultimately was based on the [[Ford Pinto]] subcompact.

The new model (dubbed and badged &quot;Mustang II&quot;) was introduced two months before the first &quot;Energy Crisis&quot; in [[1973 oil crisis|October 1973]], and its reduced size allowed it to compete more effectively against smaller imported sports coupés such as the Japanese [[Toyota Celica]] and the European [[Ford Capri]] (then Ford-built in Germany and Britain, sold in U.S. by Mercury as a [[captive import]] car). First-year sales were 385,993 cars, compared with the original Mustang's twelve-month sales record of 418,812.&lt;ref&gt;[http://auto.howstuffworks.com/1974-1975-1976-1977-1978-ford-mustang.htm &quot;1974, 1975, 1976, 1977, 1978 Ford Mustang Overview&quot; by the Auto Editors of ''Consumer Guide'', undated], retrieved on March 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lee Iacocca wanted the new car, which returned the Mustang to more than a semblance of its 1964 predecessor in size, shape, and overall styling,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last = Witzenburg
|first = Gary L.
|title = Mustang!: The Complete History of America's Pioneer Ponycar
|publisher = Automobile Quarterly Publications
|year = 1979
|page = 146
|isbn = 9780915038251}}&lt;/ref&gt; to be finished to a high standard, saying it should be &quot;a little jewel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://auto.howstuffworks.com/1974-1975-1976-1977-1978-ford-mustang2.htm &quot;The 1974 Ford Mustang: The Winning Design&quot; 1974 1975 1976 1977 1978 Ford Mustang by the Auto Editors of ''Consumer Guide'', February 15, 2007], retrieved on August 17, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; However not only was it smaller than the original car, but it was also heavier, owing to the addition of equipment needed to meet new U.S. emission and safety regulations. Performance was reduced, and despite the car's new handling and engineering features the galloping mustang emblem &quot;became a less muscular steed that seemed to be [[canter]]ing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://auto.howstuffworks.com/1974-1975-1976-1977-1978-ford-mustang5.htm &quot;1974 Ford Mustang Engines and Options&quot; 1974 1975 1976 1977 1978 Ford Mustang by the Auto Editors of ''Consumer Guide'', February 15, 2007], retrieved on August 17, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The car was available in coupé and [[hatchback]] versions. Changes introduced in 1975 included reinstatement of the 302 [[Cubic inch|CID]] [[V8]] option (called the &quot;5.0&amp;nbsp;L&quot; although its capacity was 4.94&amp;nbsp;L) and availability of an economy option called the &quot;MPG Stallion&quot;. Other changes in appearance and performance came with a &quot;Cobra II&quot; version in 1976 and a &quot;King Cobra&quot; in 1978.

== Third generation (1979–1993) ==
{{main|Ford Mustang (third generation)}}
[[Image:'87-'88 Ford Mustang 5.0.jpg|thumb|1985–1986 Ford Mustang GT]]

The 1979 Mustang was based on the larger [[Ford Fox platform|Fox platform]] (initially developed for the 1978 [[Ford Fairmont]] and [[Mercury Zephyr]]). The interior was restyled to accommodate four people in comfort despite a smaller rear seat. The [[trunk (automobile)|trunk]] was larger, as was the engine bay, for easier service access.

Body styles included a [[coupé]], ([[notchback]]), and [[hatchback]]; a convertible was offered in 1983. Available trim levels included L, GL, GLX, LX, GT, Turbo GT, SVO (1984–86), Cobra, and Cobra R (1993).

In response to slumping sales and escalating fuel prices during the early 1980s, a [[Third-generation Ford Mustang#Proposed replacement|new Mustang]] was in development. It was to be a variant of the [[Mazda MX-6]] assembled at [[AutoAlliance International]] in [[Flat Rock, Michigan]]. Enthusiasts wrote to Ford objecting to the proposed change to a front-wheel drive, Japanese-designed Mustang without a V8 option. The result was a major facelift of the [[Third-generation Ford Mustang#1987–1993|existing Mustang]] in 1987, while the MX-6 variant became the 1989 [[Ford Probe]].

*1979 served as an [[Indianapolis 500 pace cars|Indianapolis 500 pace car]] and Ford built 10,478 commemorative replicas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last = Sessler|first = Peter C.|last2 = Sessler|first2 = Nilda|title = Ford Mustang Buyer's And Restoration Guide|publisher = Sams Technical Publishing|year = 2006|page = 126|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=l_1ngoGACCUC&amp;pg=PA126&amp;dq=1979+Mustang+Indianapolis+500+Pace+Car&amp;ei=HAidS6G9Io3mygTt7ZW5Cg&amp;cd=3#v=onepage&amp;q=1979%20Mustang%20Indianapolis%20500%20Pace%20Car&amp;f=false|isbn = 9780790613260|accessdate = 2010-03-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1982 models had the option of a true 5.0 liter 302 cubic inch V8 engine instead of the 4.2 liter V8. 1983 was the first year for a 5-speed transmission.
*1985 model year received a new roller cam block, roller cam, and roller lifters.
*1986 was the first year of fuel injection.
*1988 V8 model was equipped with mass air in California cars only, then in 1989 all cars were equipped.
*1993 year had hypereutectic instead of forged pistons and was also rated at {{Convert|205|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}} instead of the previous years {{Convert|225|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mustanggt.org/93gt.htm 1993 Mustang GT&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fourth generation (1994–2004) ==
{{main|Ford Mustang (fourth generation)}}
[[File:2002FordMustang.jpg|thumb|2002 Ford Mustang Convertible]]

In 1994 the Mustang underwent its first major redesign in fifteen years. Code named &quot;SN-95&quot; by [[Ford]], it was based on an updated version of the [[rear-wheel drive]] Fox platform called &quot;Fox-4.&quot; The new styling by [[Patrick Schiavone]] incorporated several styling cues from earlier Mustangs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://auto.howstuffworks.com/1994-1995-1996-1997-1998-ford-mustang.htm &quot;1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 1998 Ford Mustang Overview&quot; by the Auto Editors of Consumer Guide, 2007-02-23], retrieved on 2010-01-01.&lt;/ref&gt; For the first time since 1973, a [[hatchback]] coupe model was unavailable.

The base model came with a [[Ford Essex V6 engine (Canadian)|3.8 OHV]] [[V6 engine|V6]] (232&amp;nbsp;cid) engine rated at {{convert|145|bhp|abbr=on}} in 1994 and 1995, or {{convert|150|bhp|abbr=on}} (1996–1998), and was mated to a standard 5-speed [[manual transmission]] or optional 4-speed [[automatic transmission|automatic]]. Though initially used in the 1994 and 1995 Mustang GT, Ford retired the 302&amp;nbsp;cid pushrod small-block V8 after nearly 40 years of use, replacing it with the newer [[Ford Modular engine|Modular]] 4.6&amp;nbsp;L (281&amp;nbsp;cid) SOHC V8 in the 1996 Mustang GT. The 4.6&amp;nbsp;L V8 was initially rated at {{convert|215|bhp|abbr=on}}, 1996–1997, but was later increased to {{convert|225|bhp|abbr=on}} in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;[http://auto.howstuffworks.com/1994-1995-1996-1997-1998-ford-mustang8.htm &quot;The 1996 Ford Mustang&quot; by the Auto Editors of ''Consumer Guide'', 2007-02-23], retrieved on 2010-01-01.&lt;/ref&gt; 

For 1999, the Mustang received Ford's [[New Edge]] styling theme with sharper contours, larger wheel arches, and creases in its bodywork, but its basic proportions, interior design, and chassis remained the same as the previous model. The Mustang's powertrains were carried over for 1999, but benefitted from new improvements. The standard 3.8&amp;nbsp;L V6 had a new split-port induction system, and was rated at {{convert|190|bhp|abbr=on}} 1999–2004,&lt;ref&gt;[http://auto.howstuffworks.com/1999-2000-2001-2002-2003-2004-ford-mustang2.htm &quot;The 1999 Ford Mustang Chassis and Engines&quot; by the Auto Editors of ''Consumer Guide'', 2007-02-27], retrieved on 2010-04-25.&lt;/ref&gt; while the Mustang GT's 4.6&amp;nbsp;L V8 saw an increase in output to {{convert|260|bhp|abbr=on}} (1999–2004), due to a new head design and other enhancements. There were also three alternate models offered in this generation: the 2001 [[Ford Mustang variants#Bullitt|Bullitt]], the 2003 and 2004 [[Ford Mustang Mach 1|Mach 1]], as well as the {{convert|305|bhp|abbr=on}} (1999) {{convert|320|bhp|abbr=on}} (2001–2002),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.insideline.com/ford/mustang/2001/first-drive-2001-ford-svt-mustang-cobra.html First Drive: 2001 Ford SVT Mustang Cobra&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mustangevolution.com/2002-mustang-cobra/ 2002 Mustang Cobra&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and {{convert|390|bhp|abbr=on}} 2003–2004&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motortrend.com/roadtests/coupes/112_0306_2003_ford_mustang_svt_cobra/index.html 2003 Ford Mustang SVT Cobra - First Drive &amp; Road Test Review - Motor Trend&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ford Mustang SVT Cobra|Cobra]].

== Fifth generation (2005- ) ==
{{main|Ford Mustang (fifth generation)}}
[[File:Ford Mustang GT CS convertible.jpg|thumb|2007–2009 Ford Mustang GT/CS convertible]]

At the 2004 [[North American International Auto Show]], Ford introduced a completely redesigned Mustang, codenamed &quot;S-197,&quot; that was based on an all-new [[Ford D2C platform|D2C]] platform for the 2005 [[model year]]. Developed under the direction of Chief Engineer [[Hau Thai-Tang]] and exterior styling designer [[Sid Ramnarace]],&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes01&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|title = 2010 Ford Mustang GT: Embracing the spirit of change
|work = The L.A. Times
|author = Neil, Dan
|date= 23 January 2009
|url = http://www.latimes.com/classified/automotive/highway1/la-fi-neil23-2009jan23,0,2175456.story}}&lt;/ref&gt; the fifth-generation Mustang's styling echoes the [[fastback]] Mustangs of the late 1960s. Ford's senior vice president of design, [[J Mays]], called it &quot;retro-futurism.&quot;

The fifth-generation Mustang is manufactured at the [[AutoAlliance International]] plant in [[Flat Rock, Michigan]]. The base model is powered by a {{Convert|210|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}} cast-iron block [[Ford Cologne V6 engine|4.0 L SOHC V6]], which replaces the 3.8&amp;nbsp;L pushrod V6 used previously. The Mustang GT features an aluminum block 4.6&amp;nbsp;L SOHC [[multi-valve|3-valve]] [[Ford Modular engine#4.6.C2.A0L|Modular]] V8 with [[Variable Cam Timing|variable camshaft timing]] (VCT) that produces {{Convert|300|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}}. The 2005 Mustang GT has an approximate weight to power ratio of {{convert|11.5|lb|abbr=on}}/bhp. The base Mustang comes with a standard [[Borg-Warner T-5 transmission|Tremec T-5]] 5-speed manual transmission while Ford's own [[Ford Bordeaux Automatic Transmissions|5R55S]] 5-speed automatic, a Mustang first, is optional. Though the Mustang GT features the same automatic transmission as the V6 model, the Tremec T-5 manual is substituted with the heavier duty [[Tremec TR-3650 transmission|Tremec TR-3650]] 5-speed manual transmission to better handle the GT's extra power.&lt;ref&gt;Ford Motor Company. [http://media.ford.com/products/presskit_display.cfm?vehicle_id=1052&amp;press_section_id=398&amp;make_id=92''2005 Mustang'']. Ford Media. 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ford announced in July 2007 that all 2008 Mustangs would have seats containing material derived from [[soybean]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title =New Twist on Green: 2008 Ford Mustang Seats Will Be Soy-Based Foam|publisher =Edmunds inside line|date=July 12, 2007|url =http://www.edmunds.com/insideline/do/News/articleId=121682| accessdate =2007-10-02}}{{dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; harking back to some of [[Henry Ford#Sidelights|Henry Ford's]] ideals.

A new option for the 2009 Mustang was the glass roof. This $1,995 option is in effect a full roof sunroof that splits the difference in price and purpose of the coupe and convertible models.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.windingroad.com/body-stylesmarket-segment/sportsgts/ford-shows-2009-glass-roof-mustang/ &quot;Ford Shows 2009 Glass Roof Mustang&quot;], Winding Road.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2010 ===
For the 2010 models, Ford unveiled a redesigned Mustang prior to the [[LA Auto Show|Los Angeles International Auto Show]]. The 2010 Mustang remains on the [[Ford D2C platform|D2C]] platform and mostly retains the previous-year's drivetrain options. The Mustang received a thoroughly revised exterior, with only the roof panel being retained, that is sculpted for a leaner, more muscular appearance and better aerodynamic performance ([[drag coefficient|coefficient of drag]] has been reduced by 4% on V6 models and 7% on GT models &lt;ref name=&quot;suspension&quot;&gt;Ford Motor Company.[http://media.ford.com/press_kits_detail.cfm?presskit_id=1982&amp;item_id=5604&amp;press_section_id=2859 &quot;2010 Mustang Steering and Suspension&quot;]. Ford Media. 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;).

The V6 for base Mustangs remains unchanged, while the Mustang GT's [[Ford Modular engine|4.6&amp;nbsp;L V8]] has been revised to specifications similar to that of the 2008–2009 Mustang Bullitt's 4.6&amp;nbsp;L V8, resulting in {{convert|315|hp|kW|abbr=on}} at 6000&amp;nbsp;rpm and {{convert|325|lbft|Nm|abbr=on}} of torque at 4250&amp;nbsp;rpm.&lt;ref name=&quot;techspecs&quot;&gt;Ford Motor Company. [http://media.ford.com/press_kits_detail.cfm?presskit_id=1982&amp;item_id=5605&amp;press_section_id=2878 &quot;2010 Mustang Technical Specifications&quot;]. Ford Media. 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Other mechanical features for the 2010 Mustang include new spring rates and dampers to improve ride quality and control, standard traction control system and stability control system on all models, and new wheel sizes. For the Mustang GT, two performance packages were made available. Other new features and options for the 2010 Mustang include [[Ford Sync|Ford SYNC]], dual-zone automatic climate control, an updated navigation system with [[Sirius Satellite Radio|Sirius]] Travel Link, a capless fuel filler, and a reverse camera system to aid in backing up. The SYNC, navigation, and the reverse camera are not available on the basic V6 coupe.

[[File:2010 Ford Mustang -- 07-18-2009.jpg|thumb|right||2010 Ford Mustang V6 coupe]]
The 2010 model year Mustang was released in the spring of 2009. Ten models were available for the 2010 Mustang, with base prices ranging from $21,395 for the basic V6 to $51,725 for the GT500 Convertible.

=== 2011 ===
Ford revised all the Mustang's engines for 2011. The new V6 is a smaller 3.7&amp;nbsp;L (227 cu. in.) aluminum block engine weighing {{convert|40|lb|abbr=on}} lighter than the outgoing version. The engine produces {{convert|305|hp|kW|abbr=on}} and {{convert|280|lbft|Nm|abbr=on}} of torque. Ford announced on December 28, 2009 that the 2011 Mustang GT would feature a 5.0 liter (302 cu. in.) engine displacement that will produce 412 horsepower and 390 ft/lbs of torque on &quot;premium fuel&quot; (gasoline with a [[Octane rating#Anti-Knock_Index_.28AKI.29|pump octane]] rating of 93); on &quot;regular fuel&quot; (gasoline with a pump octane rating of 87), these numbers fall to {{convert|402|hp|kW|abbr=on}} and {{convert|377|lbft|Nm|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;2011techspecs&quot;&gt;Ford Motor Company. [http://www.fordvehicles.com/cars/mustang/specifications/engine/ &quot;2011 Ford Mustang Full Engine Specifications&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; The power and performance that the 2011 Mustang GT puts out is largely due to the new Ford 5.0-liter V8 “Coyote” engine. The Coyote is a 32 valve (4 valves per cylinder) with Twin Independent Variable Cam Timing (TiVCT). These cams will control intake and exhaust functions of the vehicle which will maximize combustion and ultimately power. The transmission can be bought in a 6 speed automatic or manual (up from the previous 5 speed transmission). The innovative Electronic Power Assist Steering (EPAS) removes the conventional hydraulic power steering pump. The system does not use belts previously required for steering, thus drive train horsepower loss is decreased.  An optional [[Brembo]] brake upgrade is available. These brakes essentially come from the Shelby GT-500 and this the first time they will be offered on the Mustang. In addition to the upgraded brake package, Ford will throw in a pair of 19” wheels and performance tires.&lt;ref&gt;http://jautosource.blogspot.com/&lt;/ref&gt;  The Shelby GT500's 5.4L block is now made out of aluminum, instead of iron as in previous years, and is now rated at {{convert|550|hp|kW|abbr=on}} and {{Convert|510|lbft|Nm|abbr=on}} of torque. Due to being made of aluminum instead of iron, the new block is {{convert|102|lb|abbr=on}} lighter than the old one, which helps to improve fuel economy, acceleration, handling, and steering precision.&lt;ref&gt;Auto Fans. [http://autosfans.com/2011-ford-shelby-gt500/ &quot;2011 Ford Shelby GT500&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;

The V6's [[Fuel economy in automobiles#EPA_testing_procedure:_2008_and_beyond|EPA-estimated fuel economy]] is {{convert|19|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} city/{{convert|29|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} highway with the standard six-speed manual transmission, or {{convert|19|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} city/{{convert|31|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} highway with the optional six-speed automatic transmission. The 5.0L V8 is rated at {{convert|17|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} city/{{convert|26|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} highway with the standard six-speed manual transmission, or {{convert|18|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} city/{{convert|25|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} highway with the optional six-speed automatic.&lt;ref name=&quot;2011techspecs&quot;&gt;Ford Motor Company. [http://www.fordvehicles.com/cars/mustang/specifications/engine/ &quot;2011 Ford Mustang Full Engine Specifications&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; The Shelby GT500 is rated at {{convert|15|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} city/{{convert|23|mpgUS|L/km|abbr=on}} highway with the standard six-speed manual transmission.&lt;ref&gt;EPA. [http://www.fueleconomy.gov/feg/2008car1tablef.jsp?id=30038 &quot;Estimated Fuel Economy for 2011 Ford Mustang&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racing==
{{Refimprovesection|date=April 2008}}

The Mustang made its first public appearance on a racetrack little more than a month after its April 17 introduction, as [[pace car]] for the [[1964 Indianapolis 500]].&lt;ref name=fordpr/&gt;

The same year, Mustangs achieved the first of many notable competition successes, winning first and second in class in the [[Tour de France]] international rally. The car’s American competition debut, also in 1964, was in [[drag racing]], where private individuals and dealer-sponsored teams campaigned Mustangs powered by 427 cu. in. V8s.

In late 1964, Ford contracted [[Holman &amp; Moody]] to prepare ten 427-powered Mustangs to contest the [[National Hot Rod Association]]'s (NHRA) A/Factory Experimental class in the 1965 drag racing season. Five of these special Mustangs made their competition debut at the 1965 NHRA Winternationals, where they qualified in the Factory Stock Eliminator class. The car driven by Bill Lawton won the class.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cartechbooks.com/vstore/showdetl.cfm?st=0&amp;st2=0&amp;st3=0&amp;CATID=21&amp;Product_ID=2553&amp;DID=6 Morris, Charlie. &quot;Ford's 1965 Factory Experimental Mustangs&quot;, ''Car Tech Inc.'' website, undated article]. Retrieved on August 26, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

A decade later Bob Glidden won the Mustang’s first NHRA Pro Stock title.

Early Mustangs also proved successful in road racing. The GT 350 R, the race version of the [[Shelby Mustang|Shelby GT 350]], won five of the [[Sports Car Club of America]]'s (SCCA) six divisions in 1965. Drivers were Jerry Titus, Bob Johnson and [[Mark Donohue]], and Titus won the (SCCA) B-Production national championship. GT 350s won the B-Production title again in 1966 and 1967. They also won the 1966 manufacturers’ championship in the inaugural SCCA [[Trans-Am series]], and repeated the win the following year.&lt;ref name=fordpr/&gt;

In 1969, modified versions of the 428 Mach 1, Boss 429 and Boss 302 took 295 United States Auto Club-certified records at [[Bonneville Salt Flats]]. The outing included a 24-hour run on a {{convert|10|mi|km|sing=on}} course at an average speed of {{convert|157|mi/h|km/h}}. Drivers were [[Mickey Thompson]], [[Danny Ongais]], Ray Brock and Bob Ottum.&lt;ref name=fordpr/&gt;

Boss 429 engines powered [[Ford Torino]]s in 1969 and 1970 [[NASCAR]] racing.

In 1970 the Mustang won the manufacturers’ championship in the Trans-Am series once again, with [[Parnelli Jones]] and [[George Follmer]] driving. Jones won the drivers’ title. Two years later [[Dick Trickle]] won 67 short-track feature races, a national record for wins in a single season.

In 1975 Ron Smaldone's Mustang became the first-ever American car to win the Showroom Stock national championship in SCCA road racing.

Mustangs also competed in the [[IMSA]] GTO class, with wins in 1984 and 1985. In 1985 John Jones also won the 1985 GTO drivers’ championship; Wally Dallenbach Jr., John Jones and [[Doc Bundy]] won the GTO class at the [[Daytona 24 Hours]]; and Ford won its first manufacturers’ championship in road racing since 1970. Three class wins went to Lynn St. James, the first woman to win in the series.

1986 brought eight more GTO wins and another manufacturers’ title. [[Scott Pruett]] won the drivers’ championship. The GT Endurance Championship also went to Ford.

In drag racing Rickie Smith’s [[Motorcraft]] Mustang won the [[International Hot Rod Association]] [[Pro Stock]] world championship.

In 1987 Saleen Autosport Mustangs driven by [[Steve Saleen]] and [[Rick Titus]] won the SCCA Escort Endurance SSGT championship, and in [[International Motor Sports Association]] (IMSA) racing a Mustang again won the GTO class in the Daytona 24 hours. In 1989, its silver anniversary year, the Mustang won Ford its first Trans-Am manufacturers’ title since 1970, with Lynn St. James winning the drivers’ championship. In 1997, [[Tommy Kendall]]’s Roush-prepared Mustang won a record 11 consecutive races in Trans-Am to secure his third straight driver’s championship.

In 2002 John Force broke his own NHRA drag racing record by winning his 12th national championship in his Ford Mustang [[Funny Car]], Force beat that record again in 2006, becoming the first ever 14-time champion, again, driving a Mustang.&lt;ref name=fordpr/&gt;

Currently Mustangs compete in several racing series, including the [[Mustang Challenge for the Miller Cup]] and the [[KONI Challenge Series|KONI Challenge]], where it won the manufacturer's title in 2005 &amp; 2008, and the[[Canada Drift]], [[Formula Drift]] and [[D1 Grand Prix]] series. They are highly competitive in the SCCA [[Speed World Challenge]] GT Series.

As reported by Jayski.com, the Ford Mustang will be Ford's [[Car of Tomorrow]] for the NASCAR Nationwide Series in 2010, opening a new chapter in both Mustang's history and Ford's history.

== Awards ==
[[Image:2005 mustang car of the year award.JPG|thumb|2005 Canadian Car of the Year]]
The 1965 Mustang won the Tiffany Gold Medal for excellence in American design, the first automobile ever to do so.

The Mustang was on the [[Car and Driver Ten Best]] list in [[Car and Driver Ten Best#1983|1983]], [[Car and Driver Ten Best#1987|1987]], [[Car and Driver Ten Best#1988|1988]], [[Car and Driver Ten Best#2005|2005]], and [[Car and Driver Ten Best#2006|2006]]. It won the [[Motor Trend Car of the Year]] award in 1974 and 1994.

In 2005 it was runner-up to the [[Chrysler 300]] for the [[North American Car of the Year]] award and was named [[Canadian Car of the Year]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.ford.com/newsroom/feature_display.cfm?release=19987 Ford Motor Company - Featured Story - Ford Mustang is Named 2005 Canadian Car of the Year&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[California Special Mustang]]
*[[Ford Motor Company]]
*[[Ford Mustang SSP]]
*[[Ford Mustang variants]]
*[[Shelby Mustang]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
*{{cite web|url = http://www.canadiandriver.com/news/040105-7.htm|title = 2005 Mustang draws inspiration from the 60's|work = CanadianDriver|publisher = CanadianDriver Communications, Inc.|accessdate = 2004-01-11 }}
*{{cite book|author = Chilton Automotive Books|date = August 1, 1997|title = ''Ford Mustang/Mercury Cougar, 1964-73 Repair Manual''|edition = 1st|page = 450|publisher = Thomson Delmar Learning|location = Radnor, PA|isbn = 0-8019-9060-2|url = }}
*{{cite book|last = Leffingwell|first = Randy|title = Mustang Forty Years|publisher = MBI Publishing|location = Osceola|year = 2003|isbn = 0760315973 }}
*{{cite web|url = http://www.autolife.umd.umich.edu/Design/Ash_interview.htm|title = The Reminiscences of L. David Ash|work = Automobile in American Life and Society|publisher = University of Michigan-Dearborn and The Henry Ford|accessdate = 2005-01-30}}

== External links ==
&lt;!--
***********************({{No More Links}}) ***************************
*Please be cautious in adding more links to this article. Wikipedia *
*is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. *
*                 *
*  Excessive or inappropriate links Will-Be-Deleted.   *
*See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details. *
*                 *
*If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or *
*replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link *
*to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) *
*and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.   *
**********************({{No More Links}}) ****************************
--&gt;
{{commonscat}}
*[http://www.fordvehicles.com/cars/mustang/?space=Cars Official site]
*{{dmoz|Recreation/Autos/Makes_and_Models/Ford/Mustang/|Ford Mustang}}
*[http://www.life.com/image/first/in-gallery/23256/american-classic-ford-mustang American Classic: Ford Mustang] - slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''

{{Ford Mustang}}

[[Category:Ford Mustang]]
[[Category:Ford vehicles|Mustang]]
[[Category:1960s automobiles]]
[[Category:1970s automobiles]]
[[Category:1980s automobiles]]
[[Category:1990s automobiles]]
[[Category:2000s automobiles]]
[[Category:2010s automobiles]]
[[Category:Vehicles introduced in 1964]]
[[Category:Coupes]]
[[Category:Convertibles]]
[[Category:Hatchbacks]]
[[Category:Rear wheel drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Motor vehicles manufactured in the United States]]

[[af:Ford Mustang]]
[[ar:فورد موستانج]]
[[bg:Форд Мустанг]]
[[ca:Ford Mustang]]
[[cs:Ford Mustang]]
[[da:Ford Mustang]]
[[de:Ford Mustang]]
[[es:Ford Mustang]]
[[fa:فورد موستانگ]]
[[fr:Ford Mustang]]
[[ko:포드 머스탱]]
[[hi:फोर्ड मस्टैंग (Ford Mustang)]]
[[is:Ford Mustang]]
[[it:Ford Mustang]]
[[he:פורד מוסטנג]]
[[ka:ფორდ მუსტანგი]]
[[lv:Ford Mustang]]
[[lt:Ford Mustang]]
[[hu:Ford Mustang]]
[[nl:Ford Mustang]]
[[ja:フォード・マスタング]]
[[no:Ford Mustang]]
[[nn:Ford Mustang]]
[[pl:Ford Mustang]]
[[pt:Ford Mustang]]
[[ru:Ford Mustang]]
[[simple:Ford Mustang]]
[[sk:Ford Mustang]]
[[fi:Ford Mustang]]
[[sv:Ford Mustang]]
[[th:ฟอร์ด มัสแตง]]
[[tr:Ford Mustang]]
[[uk:Ford Mustang]]
[[zh:福特野馬]]</text>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
