<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.4/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.4/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.4.xsd" version="0.4" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.16wmf4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Subaru Impreza</title>
    <id>527976</id>
    <revision>
      <id>369348787</id>
      <timestamp>2010-06-21T12:39:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OSX</username>
        <id>1669452</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Third generation - &quot;GE&quot;/&quot;GH&quot;/&quot;GR&quot; */ Replaced sedan front 3/4 view image with rear 3/4 view image</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the high-performance versions of the Impreza|Subaru Impreza WRX|Subaru Impreza WRX STI}}
{{for|the off-road, outdoor activity version of the Impreza Sport Wagon|Subaru Outback}}

{{Infobox Automobile
|image          = [[File:2007 Subaru Impreza Front Quarter.jpg|250px|2007 Subaru Impreza RS hatchback (Australia)]]
|name           = Subaru Impreza
|manufacturer   = [[Subaru]]
|parent_company = [[Fuji Heavy Industries]]
|production     = 1993–present
|assembly       = [[Ōta, Gunma|Ōta]], [[Gunma]], [[Japan]] (1993-present) &lt;br /&gt;[[Lafayette, Indiana]], [[USA]] (2003-present)
|class          = [[Compact car|Compact]]
|predecessor    = [[Subaru Leone|Subaru Leone/Loyale]]
}}
The '''Subaru Impreza''' is a [[compact car]] that was first introduced by [[Subaru]] in 1993.

&quot;Impreza&quot; is a coined word, deriving from an originally [[Italian language|Italian]] word, impresa, meaning a feat or achievement. In [[Polish language|Polish]], &quot;Impreza&quot; means &quot;party&quot;, &quot;event&quot; or &quot;show&quot;.

The Impreza was introduced after the popular [[Subaru Leone|Leone]]/[[Subaru Loyale|Loyale]] was cancelled with the aging [[Subaru EA engine|EA series]] engine. The Impreza was introduced with the popular [[Subaru EJ engine|EJ series]] engine found in the larger [[Subaru Legacy]]. In Japan, the Impreza sells more than the larger Legacy due to Japanese [[Vehicle size class#Japan|vehicle size legislation]], which offers a reduced tax liability because of its smaller exterior dimensions.

Compared to vehicles in a similar size class such as [[Toyota Corolla]], [[Honda Civic]], [[Nissan Sentra]], [[Suzuki SX4]], [[Mitsubishi Lancer]] (including [[Mitsubishi Lancer Evolution]]) and [[Mazda 323|Mazda Protegé]]/[[Mazda Axela]], only the Impreza has always offered [[Four-wheel drive|AWD]]. Subaru Impreza made this feature standard equipment in all trims, while its competitor, [[Mitsubishi Lancer]] puts this feature to [[Ralliart]] trims and [[Mitsubishi Lancer Evolution|Evolution]] versions. Subaru produces a lower volume of slightly upscale, well-equipped, sportier Impreza models, unlike other contemporaries in the compact category that offer [[economy car|no-frills base trims]].
&lt;ref name=&quot;motortrend1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.motortrend.com/roadtests/sedans/112_0707_2007_honda_civic_vs_2007_hyundai_elantra_vs_2007_mitsubishi_lancer_vs_2007_nissan_sentra_comparison/mitsubishi_lancer.html |title=2007 Honda Civic vs 2007 Hyundai Elantra vs 2007 Mitsubishi Lancer vs 2007 Nissan Sentra - Comfort |publisher=Motor Trend |date=2007-02-26 |accessdate=2009-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Subaru chose to continue their longstanding use of the [[boxer engine]] in the Impreza. According to Subaru, their configuration of the engine inline with the transmission minimizes body roll due to the lower center of gravity compared with offset engines in most other vehicles. This is similar to the design of the [[Citroen 2CV]], providing light weight and compact, economic design for basic cars. The boxer design provides good vibration mitigation due to the principles of a [[Engine balance|balanced engine]] because the movement of each piston is largely countered by a piston in the opposing cylinder bank, eliminating the need for a counter-rotating weighted crankshaft ([[harmonic balancer]]), but with some vibration from offsets. [[Torque steer]] is also reduced with this type of powertrain layout since the front drive shafts are of equal length and weight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.subaru.com/sub/misc/coretech/index.html
 |title=Core Technologies
 |accessdate=2008-03-30
 |publisher=subaru.com
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{commonscat|Subaru Impreza}}

== First generation - &quot;GC&quot;/&quot;GF&quot;/&quot;GM&quot; ==
{{Infobox Automobile generation
|image         = [[Image:93-96 Subaru Impreza.jpg|250px|1997-2001 Subaru Impreza sedan (US)]]
|name          = First generation
|production    = 1993–2001
|assembly      = [[Ōta, Gunma|Ōta]], [[Gunma]], [[Japan]]
|engine        = 1.8&amp;nbsp;[[Liter|L]] 110&amp;nbsp;[[Horsepower|hp]] [[Flat-4|H4]] &lt;br /&gt;2.0&amp;nbsp;[[Liter|L]] Turbo 208-280&amp;nbsp;[[Horsepower|hp]] [[Flat-4|H4]] &lt;br /&gt;2.2&amp;nbsp;[[Liter|L]] 145&amp;nbsp;[[Horsepower|hp]] [[Flat-4|H4]] &lt;br /&gt;2.5&amp;nbsp;[[Liter|L]] 165&amp;nbsp;[[Horsepower|hp]] [[Flat-4|H4]]
|length        = 4375 mm (172.2&amp;nbsp;in)
|width         = 1705 mm (67.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|wheelbase     = 2520 mm (99.2&amp;nbsp;in)
|height        = 1410 mm (55.5&amp;nbsp;in)&lt;br /&gt;1430 mm (56.3 in) (1999-2001 Outback Sport)
|fuel_capacity = 15.9 [[Imperial units|US Gallons]]  &lt;ref&gt;http://www.cars101.com/impreza_archive93_96.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|body_style    = 2-door [[coupe]]&lt;br /&gt;4-door [[sedan (car)|sedan]]&lt;br /&gt;5-door [[station wagon]]
|transmission  = 4-speed [[Automatic transmission|automatic]]&lt;br /&gt;5-speed [[Manual transmission|manual]]
|weight=1220 kg
|layout        = Boxer [[Front-engine design|Front engine]], [[front-wheel drive]] / [[four-wheel drive]] 
|related       = [[Subaru Forester]]
}}

Introduced in November 1993, the Impreza was offered in either [[front wheel drive]] (FWD) or [[all wheel drive]] (AWD) versions and as a four-door [[sedan (car)|sedan]]/saloon or five-door [[station wagon]]/estate. According to a ''[[Motor Trend]]'' article written March 1992 on page 26, the name of Subaru's new compact was, initially, to be called the [[Subaru Leone|Loyale]], displaying an official photograph of the 4-door sedan. In late 1995, a two-door [[coupe]] was introduced. The Impreza, like many Subaru-built [[car]]s, was equipped with a [[flat engine]], a distinguishing Subaru characteristic.  Initial engine choices included 1.6, 1.8 and 2.0-litre naturally-aspirated engines as well as the [[Turbocharger|turbocharged]] and [[Intercooler|intercooled]] 2.0-litre engine.  The basic turbocharged motor, the '''EJ20''', produced from {{convert|244|PS|kW bhp|0|abbr=on}} to {{convert|210|kW|PS bhp|0|abbr=on}} in Japanese market [[Subaru Impreza WRX|WRX]] trim depending on model and year.  Outside Japan, the turbocharged model was initially rated at {{convert|211|PS|kW bhp|0|abbr=on}} and marketed as the 2.0 Turbo, 2.0 GT, 2.0 GT Turbo, 2.0 WRX, or Turbo 2000 AWD in the United Kingdom.

Trim levels were LX, GL and Sport. LX models were front-wheel drive, and powered by a 1.6-litre engine; these were four-door only.
GL trim levels were either front-wheel drive (Subaru badged these 2WD) or all-wheel-drive (badged AWD); cars launched in 1993 had a choice of 1.6 and 1.8 [[flat-4]] engines, the 1.6 being available with 2WD, the 1.8 an AWD version only. From 1996, the 1.6 and 1.8 versions were dropped (in the European market), and replaced by a 2.0-[[litre]] engine. Sport versions had alloy wheels, and a 2.0-litre engine only. These were &quot;warm hatch&quot; versions which were similar to the WRX, albeit less adorned.

In 1994, Subaru introduced [[Subaru Technica International]] (STi) versions of the Impreza in the [[Japanese Domestic Market]] (JDM) and European Domestic Market (EDM). These models were upgraded from the WRX in many categories, including blueprinted performance-tuned engines, transmissions, and suspensions.  The [[Subaru Impreza WRX STi|STi]] versions of the Impreza were immensely successful in rallies and popular among street racers.  The first STi models featured higher power ratings than the WRX, while later versions of both WRX and STi were rated at {{convert|280|PS|kW bhp|0|abbr=on}} due to the Japanese manufacturers' informal agreements around power ratings.  Its top [[speed]] was electronically limited at {{convert|180|km/h|mph|abbr=on}} and it had a 0–100&amp;nbsp;[[Kilometers per hour|km/h]] time of 4.9&amp;nbsp;[[second]]s in the UK Impreza Turbo {{convert|218|PS|kW bhp|0|abbr=on}} version. 2006 WRX STI claimed 0 to 100&amp;nbsp;km/h in 5.4 seconds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.caradvice.com.au/509/subaru-impreza-wrx-sti-2006-my06/ |title=Subaru Impreza WRX STi 2006 MY06 |work=Australian Car Advice |date=2007-07-15 |accessdate=2008-02-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; RA (Race Altered) versions of the WRX and STi were also available in the Japanese market.  Targeted for race and rally, the RA versions were generally lighter in weight; featuring reduced soundproofing, manual windows, no air conditioning, and added racing features such as more robust engines, driver controlled center differentials, and shorter gearing.

Special editions of the Impreza were very common in Japan and Europe, many coinciding with a significant World Rally Championship victory.  These editions included the [[Series McRae]], [[555]], [[Catalunya]], [[Terzo]], [[Subaru impreza RB5|RB5]], [[P1]], and [[22B]], the latter still considered by many to be the ultimate Impreza of all time with its wide arched rally style body.

During this generation, Subaru made a limited edition Impreza Sport Wagon called the CasaBlanca,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cardatabase.net/?pid=00079059 |title=CarDatabase.net - Subaru Impreza Casablanca Wagon |accessdate=2008-02-06 |work=CarDatabase.net }}&lt;/ref&gt; which had a [[retro]] front and rear end treatment, which was inspired by the popular [[kei car]] [[Subaru Vivio|Subaru Vivio Bistro]] styling package and [[Subaru Sambar#1990-1998|Subaru Sambar Dias Classic]]. The Sport Wagon was also offered with the WRX turbocharged engine, and was called the [[Subaru Outback#Subaru Outback Sport|Gravel Express]]. 

The Impreza received an external facelift for the 1997 model year, followed by an interior redesign in 1998, using the new redesigned dashboard from the Forester.

The European 1999-2000 turbo model received further upgrades in the form of more parts from the STi range. The front brakes became Subaru branded 4-pot calipers with 294&amp;nbsp;mm discs, the wheels having become {{convert|16|in|mm|adj=on}} lightweight alloys from 1998 - previously {{convert|15|in|mm|adj=on}}, vented rear discs, the Sti 4 high level wing was fitted to the saloon, Sti style front bucket seats and firmer suspension. The phase 2 engine now fitted developed {{convert|160|kW|PS bhp|0|abbr=on}}, an increase of {{convert|5|kW|PS bhp|0|abbr=on}} over the previous model.

The story of the North American Impreza is much different than the rest of the world.  North American markets never received a turbocharged version of the first generation Impreza (it was heavily rumored in 1998 and 1999).  Subaru never had a performance image in North America, so Subaru initially offered the Impreza with the 1.8L engine only, with either front- or all-wheel drive; a 2.2-liter engine became optional in 1995.  Subaru later decided to emphasize all-wheel drive, making it standard on every Impreza (and Legacy) from 1997 onwards.

There was a minority that knew of the Impreza's accomplishments overseas and was very interested in having a high-performance Impreza.  To test the waters for a full-fledged turbo model Subaru showcased a turbocharged version of the Impreza at various car shows around the country. The vehicle was named the 2.5RX and is now located in Subaru of America's Cherry Hill, NJ storage facility. Subsequently the 2.5RS performance model was introduced in 1998 (the same year the 1.8-liter engine was dropped).  A naturally-aspirated {{convert|165|bhp|kW PS|0|abbr=on}} 2.5L [[DOHC]] engine and larger brakes, borrowed from the [[Subaru Legacy|Legacy]], were fitted into the coupe body with gold-colored 16&quot; five-spoke wheels.  The 2.5RS also featured several external cues from its overseas brethren such as hood vents, a hood scoop, and a rally-inspired rear spoiler.  The 1999 model featured several changes: the newly designed &quot;Phase II&quot; [[SOHC]] version of the same 2.5L engine featured a slightly higher peak torque ({{convert|225|N.m|kgf.m ftlbf|abbr=on}} vs. {{convert|220|N.m|kgf.m ftlbf|abbr=on}}), the wheels turned to a standard silver, the interior got an update, and US versions became visually similar to their Japanese contemporaries with an updated front bumper borrowed from the Japanese Version 6 Impreza WRX STi.  2.5RS models became available in [[sedan (car)|sedan]] form in 2000.

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Subaru Impreza front 20071029.jpg|European Subaru Impreza Wagon

Image:1st_Subaru_Impreza_RS.jpg|Subaru Impreza 2.5RS sedan (US)

Image:1999_impreza_RS_coupe.jpg|Subaru Impreza 2.5RS coupe (US)

Image:1st Subaru Impreza L wagon.jpg|Subaru Impreza L Wagon (US)

Image:SUBARU IMPREZA GC8V.JPG|Subaru Impreza WRX GC8V, [[Japanese domestic market|JDM]] version.

File:1994-1995 Subaru Impreza GX sedan 03.jpg|1994-1995 Subaru Impreza GX sedan.

File:1994-1995 Subaru Impreza GX sedan 02.jpg|1994-1995 Subaru Impreza GX sedan.

Image:Subaru Impreza Casa Blanca 001.JPG|Subaru Impreza&lt;br /&gt; Casa Blanca
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{clear}}

== Second generation - &quot;GD&quot;/&quot;GG&quot; ==
{{Infobox Automobile generation
|image         = [[Image:2005.impreza.gx.sport.jpg|250px|2005 Subaru Impreza GX Sport in WR Blue (UK)]]
|name          = Second generation
|production    = 2000–2007
|assembly      = [[Ōta, Gunma|Ōta]], [[Gunma]], [[Japan]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Lafayette, Indiana]] [[USA]]
|engine        = 1.5&amp;nbsp;L 125hp (EJ15)100HP &lt;br /&gt;2.0&amp;nbsp;L 125hp (GX)&lt;br /&gt; 2.5&amp;nbsp;L 165&amp;nbsp;hp [[Flat-4|H4]] (2001-05)&lt;br /&gt;2.5&amp;nbsp;L 173&amp;nbsp;hp [[Flat-4|H4]] (2006-07)&lt;br /&gt;2.0/2.5&amp;nbsp;L Turbo-charged 227&amp;nbsp;hp [[Flat-4|H4]] (WRX 2002-07)&lt;br /&gt;2.5&amp;nbsp;L Turbo-charged 300&amp;nbsp;hp [[Flat-4|H4]] (WRX STi 2004-07)
|length        = 173.4&amp;nbsp;in (2002–03)&lt;br /&gt;173.8 in (2004-05)&lt;br /&gt;175.8&amp;nbsp;in (2006–07)
|width         = 66.7&amp;nbsp;in (wagon, 2006–07 sedan)&lt;br /&gt;68.1&amp;nbsp;in (2002–03 sedan)&lt;br /&gt;68.5 in (2004-05 sedan)&lt;br /&gt;67.3 in (Outback Sport)
|wheelbase     = 99.4&amp;nbsp;in
|height        = 58.5&amp;nbsp;in (2002–05 wagon)&lt;br /&gt;57.7&amp;nbsp;in (2005–07)&lt;br /&gt;56.7&amp;nbsp;in (2002–05 sedan)&lt;br /&gt;60.6 in (2004-07 Outback Sport)&lt;br /&gt;60.2 in (2002-03 Outback Sport)
|fuel_capacity =
|body_style    = 4–door [[sedan (car)|sedan]]&lt;br /&gt;5–door [[station wagon]]
|transmission  = 4–speed [[Automatic transmission|automatic]]&lt;br /&gt;5–speed [[Manual transmission|manual]]&lt;br /&gt;6–speed manual
|layout        = Boxer [[Front-engine design|Front engine]] / [[four wheel drive]]
|related       = [[Subaru Forester]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Saab 9-2X]]
}}

Subaru introduced the &quot;New Age&quot; Impreza to the world market in 2000.  The second generation Impreza was intended to be larger, safer, stiffer, more refined, and more responsive.  For many enthusiasts, the changes in the new car made it less desirable because it was heavier and slower with less of a raw edge to it.  The WRX Sedan had a 20&amp;nbsp;mm wider track than its predecessor to aid handling, while the wagon remained the same.  The coupe model was no longer available.  The disliked headlamp styling of the New Age Impreza was polarizing, but the improvements to the car brought greater mainstream acceptance.

For quick and easy reference to the different exteriors, some Subaru Impreza owners use nicknames based on the headlights. Each relates to a creature that has similar looking eyes: 2000-2002 are 'bug eyes' / 2002-2005 are 'crocodile' or 'blob eyes' / 2004-2007 are 'hawk eyes'.

In the United States, release of the basic {{convert|227|bhp|kW PS|0|abbr=on}} 2.0&amp;nbsp;L turbocharged Impreza, the WRX, did not occur until the 2002 model year, and the Impreza WRX STi was delayed until the 2004 model year.  The US version of the STi includes various departures from the Japanese and European counterparts, such as a turbocharged 2.5&amp;nbsp;L '''EJ257''' engine, rather than the [[twin turbo#Sequential twin-turbo|twin scroll turbo]] 2.0&amp;nbsp;L engine sold elsewhere. All 2006 American Imprezas use some form of the 2.5&amp;nbsp;L EJ25 engine since naturally aspirated and turbo charged are available. Start from 2003, the US-spec Impreza was built in [[Lafayette, Indiana]] [[USA]] for celebrate ten years of Impreza and solving the import problems.

[[Image:04-05 Subaru Impreza 2.5RS.jpg|thumb|left|2004 Subaru Impreza 2.5 RS]]
Some customers' and the press' negative reaction to the New Age Impreza's styling forced Subaru to facelift the car in 2003 for 2004 model year, with more conventional, rectangular headlamps, nicknamed 'crocodile eyes' (although many still use the 'blob eyes' nickname). For the US market, the facelifted Impreza was offered as 2.5 RS Sedan and Wagon, 2.5 Outback Sport Wagon, WRX Sedan and Wagon, and the new WRX STi Sedan. Sport Package was optional for the RS, and the WRX could be ordered with Premium Package. The RS, Outback Sport, and WRX are available with manual or automatic transmission, while the sole transmission for the STi is 6 speed manual.

All 2006 Imprezas, including the performance models, have been redesigned again with the controversial &quot;jet intake and wings&quot; grille first debuted on the [[Subaru B9 Tribeca]] [[crossover SUV]], along with new headlights (nicknamed 'hawk eyes'), taillights, and bumpers. Opinion on this style is split, but is generally regarded as better applied on the Impreza than the Tribeca. The grille design was dropped in the 3rd generation Impreza, due to the restyling. The 2.5 RS was dropped from the line up, and replaced by the base model 2.5i.

The most basic Impreza in Japan is '''1.5 i''' with 1.5 liter EJ15 [[SOHC]] engine. The '''1.5 R''' comes with the 1.5&amp;nbsp;L [[DOHC]] engine with [[AVCS]], but is only available with automatic transmission, whereas the 1.5i model is available with either [[Automatic transmission|automatic]] or [[manual transmission]]. For both models, AWD and 2WD versions are available. Option packages for either the 1.5i or 1.5R include wheel type, size, bucket seats, and white LED illuminated gauge meters. Starting with model year 2006, the EJ15 was replaced with the new [[List of Subaru engines#Subaru EL engine|EL15]]

In 2005, Subaru made their [[AVCS]] standard on all engines used in the Impreza.

For export market, the all-wheel drive '''1.6 TS''' is offered in [[Singapore]] and other Asian countries. The 1.5 sedan is normal body similar to the Sports Wagon. The TS shares wide body with WRX and WRX STI.

=== 2004 ===
Models offered in [[Australia]] in 2004 included the GX (2.0&amp;nbsp;L [[Internal combustion engine|engine]], this model has become the baseline Impreza in Australia), RV (2.0&amp;nbsp;L engine, styled for active lifestyles, similar to the USA-spec Impreza Outback Sport), RS (2.5&amp;nbsp;L engine, sport model) along with the WRX and STi version thereof. The RX model has been abandoned in Australia, and its position in the Impreza line-up has been subsumed by the GX (which had formerly been a sparsely outfitted budget model).  A variant of the RS for Australia is the RS-X, which whilst technically not a naturally-aspirated version of the WRX as is often claimed, does feature many WRX components, including wheels and brakes, in a package powered by the 2.5 litre drivetrain.

=== 2005-2007 ===
In late 2004 a new range was released; including the entry-level 2.0i (formerly GX), RV, 2.0R (formerly RS), WRX and WRX STi models. The 2.0R changed from a 2.5 L engine to a slightly more powerful 2.0 L engine; while the turbocharged WRX changed from a 2.0 L engine to a 2.5 L engine. The [[automatic transmission]] was dropped from the WRX, despite the popularity of the sports shift automatic in other Subarus such as the [[Subaru Outback|Outback]]. In 2006 the automatic transmission was added to the Limited package, which includes heated leather seats, power mirrors, heated wiper blades and a [[sunroof]]. Side airbags were added as standard across the range. Subaru Impreza WRXs have been bought by [[National Gendarmerie|French Gendarmerie]] for its Motorway patrols.
At the New York Auto Show, Subaru introduced a new WRX.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autoblog.com/2007/04/05/new-york-auto-show-2008-subaru-impreza-wrx-takes-the-stage/ |title=New York Auto Show: 2008 Subaru Impreza WRX takes the stage |work=[[Autoblog]] |accessdate=2008-02-06 |date=2007-04-05 |author=Eric Bryant}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:2002-2003 Subaru Impreza -- 07-30-2009.jpg |2002-2003 Subaru Impreza sedan (US)
Image:06-07 Subaru Impreza 2.5i.jpg|2006-2007 Subaru Impreza 2.5i sedan (US)
Image:Subaru_Impreza_rear_20071231.jpg|2005-2007 Subaru Impreza wagon (EU)
Image:Subaru police car.JPG|Subaru Impreza 1.6 TS used by the [[Singapore Police Force]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{clear}}

== Third generation - &quot;GE&quot;/&quot;GH&quot;/&quot;GR&quot; ==
{{Infobox Automobile generation
|image         = [[File:3rd generation Subaru  Impreza.jpg|250px|Subaru Impreza hatchback]]
|name          = Third generation
|production    = 2007–present
|assembly      = [[Ōta, Gunma|Ōta]], [[Gunma]], [[Japan]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Lafayette, Indiana]] [[USA]]
|engine        = 1.5&amp;nbsp;L 107 hp [[Flat-4|H4]] &lt;br /&gt; 2.0&amp;nbsp;L 150 hp [[Flat-4|H4]] &lt;br /&gt; 2.5&amp;nbsp;L 170 hp [[Flat-4|H4]] (2.5i)&lt;br /&gt;2.5&amp;nbsp;L Turbo-charged 224 hp [[Flat-4|H4]] (WRX (2008) &amp; GT (2009-present))&lt;br /&gt;2.5&amp;nbsp;L Turbo-charged 265 hp [[Flat-4|H4]] (WRX (2009-present))&lt;br /&gt;2.5&amp;nbsp;L Turbo-charged 305 hp [[Flat-4|H4]] (WRX STi (2008-present))
|length        = sedan: 180.3&amp;nbsp;in (4580&amp;nbsp;mm)&lt;br /&gt;hatchback: 173.8&amp;nbsp;in (4415&amp;nbsp;mm)
|width         = 68.5&amp;nbsp;in (1740&amp;nbsp;mm) 
|wheelbase     = 103.1&amp;nbsp;in (2620&amp;nbsp;mm)
|height        = 58.1&amp;nbsp;in (1475&amp;nbsp;mm)&lt;br /&gt;Outback Sport: {{Auto in|58.3|0}}
|weight={{convert|1394|kg|lb|0}}
|fuel_capacity = 
|body_style    = 4–door [[sedan (car)|sedan]]&lt;br /&gt;5–door [[hatchback]]
|transmission  = 4–speed [[Automatic transmission|automatic]] (w/SPORTSHIFT manual-mode)&lt;br /&gt;or 5–speed [[Automatic transmission|automatic]] (w/SPORTSHIFT manual-mode) (WRX STi A-line only)&lt;br /&gt;or 5–speed [[Manual transmission|manual]]&lt;br /&gt;or 6–speed [[Manual transmission|manual]]
|layout        = Boxer [[Front-engine design|Front engine]] / [[all wheel drive]]
|related       = [[Subaru Forester]] &lt;br&gt; [[Subaru Exiga]]
}}

=== 2008 ===
[[File:2008-2009 Subaru Impreza R sedan 02.jpg|left|thumb|2008–2009 Subaru Impreza R sedan (Australia)]]

On 2 April 2007, Subaru officially unveiled the next generation [[Subaru Impreza WRX|Impreza WRX]] at the 2007 [[New York Auto Show]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AB2008release&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autoblog.com/2007/04/03/officially-official-subaru-releases-full-details-on-2008-imprez/ |title=Officially Official: Subaru releases full details on 2008 Impreza |accessdate=2007-04-24 |last=Nunez |first=Alex |date=2007-04-03 |publisher=[[Autoblog]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to its usual rival, the [[Mitsubishi Lancer]], the Impreza WRX is increasingly being positioned as a 'practical' performance car - the suspension for instance is more accommodating of everyday roads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.edmunds.com/subaru/impreza/review.html |title=Subaru Impreza Review |publisher=Edmunds.com |date= |accessdate=2009-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.edmunds.com/subaru/impreza/2008/review.html |title=2008 Subaru Impreza Review |publisher=Edmunds.com |date= |accessdate=2009-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Similar to the marketing of the Lancer, Subaru plans to offer a lower volume of slightly upscale, well-equipped, sportier Impreza models, unlike other contemporaries such as the [[Honda Civic]], [[Mazda3]], and [[Toyota Corolla]] that offer [[economy car|no-frills base trims]].
&lt;ref name=&quot;motortrend1&quot;/&gt;  The new Impreza is offered as both a 4-door sedan and 5-door hatchback.

The new base model Impreza is slightly longer, wider and has a longer wheel base. The dashboard in the Impreza is much more open and is easy to configure. Two Subaru traditions have been ended with the new Impreza: the parking light switch atop the steering column is no longer present, and for the first time the windows have frames to improve [[Noise, Vibration, and Harshness|NVH]] levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = Subaru Impreza | year = 2007 | magazine = [[Wheels magazine]]: July 2007 | page = 198 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:2008 Subaru Impreza 2.5i hatch rear.jpg|thumb|left|2008 Subaru Impreza 2.5i hatchback (US)]]

In the Japanese domestic market the range comprises the 1.5 litre 15S using the [[List of Subaru engines#Subaru EL engine|EL15]] series engine, the 2.0 litre 20S and the 2.0 litre turbocharged S-GT using the EJ20 series engine. Variations are found in other markets around the world: In Australia the range at launch included three 2.0 litre models (the R, RX and RS) and a 2.5 litre turbocharged WRX.

In the United States market (the US and Canadian markets were the only ones to receive the sedan until it made its Japanese debut in fall 2008 as ''''Impreza Anesis'''') for the 2008 model year, the model range consists of the 2.5 liter, 2.5i and Outback Sport and the 2.5 liter turbocharged WRX. Both the 2.5 and the 2.5i are electronically limited from surpassing {{convert|190|km/h|mi/h|abbr=on}}. The EJ253 engine carries over from the previous generation to power the 2.5i and the EJ255 engine carries over from the previous generation (although it now uses many external engine components from the [[Subaru Legacy|Legacy GT]]) to power the turbocharged [[Subaru Impreza WRX|WRX]] trim levels.  In the Canadian market, the base Impreza 2.5i model received upgrades for the 2009 model year, including rear disc brakes, electronic stability control and traction control, and body-colored door handles, features previously only found on the 2.5 Sport and more expensive trims. The North America Impreza has no mention of an approved towing capacity while identical models in other markets have an official tow rating.  The US-built Impreza will continue assembly, but the WRX STi has paused - due to the economical problems.

From September 2007 the Impreza range in Australia has been changed with models designated  R, RX, RS and WRX. Initially only hatch models were offered. The R, RX and RS all share the same engine - a new 2.0 L, with {{convert|110|kW|PS bhp|0|abbr=on}} @ 6400 rpm and 196 Nm @ 3200 rpm. Subaru recommends that the new engines be run on 95 RON premium unleaded fuel. Another noticeable difference from the Japanese Impreza is the removal of the &quot;Engine Start&quot; button from the Australian model. The iconic WRX has largely unchanged engine power output of {{convert|169|kW|PS bhp|0|abbr=on}} and 320 Nm from its 2.5 L engine. As with previous versions, there will only be a manual version of the WRX. The weight of the car also has been lightened (by ~50 lbs) to just 1400&amp;nbsp;kg, and gives the WRX a 0–100&amp;nbsp;km/h time of 5.8 seconds. In contrast, curb weight of the standard Impreza model is ~60 lbs heavier, although still lighter than the WRX trim level.

In Israel, the Impreza is denoted as the B3, and three styles are offered: the B3 1.5, with a 1.5 liter engine, the B3 2.0 and the B3 2.0 Sport, both with 2.0 liter engines. Four-door and five-door models are available for each engine type, ranging from the basic R class, to the medium RX and top RXI class. No 2.5 liter engine option is available.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.subaru.co.il/models_b3.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Impreza20RWhiteFL1PP.jpg|thumb|right|Subaru Impreza 2.0 R Hatchback]]
The third generation Impreza is sold in certain Asian countries in 1.5 R, 2.0 R, 2.0 S-GT, 2.5 WRX, and 2.5 WRX STI trim levels. In [[Indonesia]], the Impreza is only available as 5 door Hatchback only, but all trim levels are offered.
The 1.5 R and 2.0 R can be ordered with Dual Range 5 speed manual, or 4 speed automatic SPORTSHIFT electronically-controlled transmission. However, in [[Singapore]] and [[Thailand]], the Impreza 1.5 R, 2.0 R, and 2.5 WRX are also offered as 4 door Sedan.

The latest-generation of the WRX STI which is built as &quot;wide body&quot; hatchback only debuted in the Tokyo Auto Show in October 2007. The release date for a US launch was in March 2008.  The WRX STI chassis code is GR, different from the GH used for the &quot;standard body&quot; hatchback WRX chassis. The Japanese WRX STI is powered by 2.0 liter improved EJ207 engine with twin scroll turbo, while the American and other export models has 2.5 liter EJ257 with single scroll turbo. The Impreza WRX STI features a Multi-Mode Driver Controlled Centre Differential (DCCD).

====Facelift Model====
[[File:2010 Subaru Impreza sedan -- 03-13-2010.jpg|thumb|200px|right|2010 Subaru Impreza sedan (US)]]
A facelifted 2010 model of the Subaru Impreza went on sale in late 2009, receiving a new grille.

In the 2010 New York International Auto Show, Subaru unveiled the 2011 model year &quot;wide body&quot; Impreza WRX Sedan and Hatchback, as well as the Impreza WRX STI 4 door Sedan. The new STI Sedan features high rear spoiler similar to the old STI.

==== Safety ====
Safety of the car has been increased with range wide inclusion of Stability/Traction control as standard in some markets.
In early September 2007, the [[IIHS]] crash-tested the 2.5i 5-door Impreza and gave it the highest ranking available due 
to the test results the car achieved, continuing Subaru's reputation for producing cars that consistently earn the institutes highest rating.&lt;ref name=&quot;iihs&quot;/&gt;

The Impreza also achieved a 5 Star Safety Rating, and a 4 Star Pedestrian Safety rating in the [[Australasian New Car Assessment Program|ANCAP]] crash tests.

==== Diesel ====
A boxer diesel engine, called the [[List of Subaru engines#Subaru EE engine (diesel)|Subaru EE]], for European Impreza models was introduced at the 2008 [[Paris Motor Show]]. The diesel Impreza was made available for sale in several European countries in early 2009, with the 2.0 litre turbodiesel engine of 150 horsepower. Two models are available as of July 2009, 2.0 TD and 2.0 TD Sport, which is better equipped.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.subaru.fi/datasheet/subaruPricelist.pdf |title=Subaru pricelist 2009 Finland |accessdate=2009-07-14 |format=PDF |language=fi |work=Subaru}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reputation ==
Subaru uses the Impreza chassis for the mechanical underpinnings of the [[Subaru Forester|Forester]], a small [[crossover SUV]] designed to compete in the segment comprising the [[Honda CR-V]] and [[Ford Escape]].

As a result of GM's investment in Fuji Heavy Industries and ownership of Saab, the [[badge engineered]] [[Saab 9-2X]] used the second generation Impreza wagon, released in 2005 (given the rally-derived &quot;Saab Rally Wagon&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.azcentral.com/class/marketplace/cars/0612wheels12saabintro.html |title=Saab, Subaru team up for niche 'Saabaru' |date=2004-06-12 |accessdate=2008-02-20 |author=Bob Golfen |publisher=azcentral.com }}&lt;/ref&gt; which was discontinued in 2006 due to the dissolution of the Subaru-GM partnership.

Subaru sold a cosmetically altered (in the [[neoclassic (automobile)|neoclassic]] style) sedan and wagon in Asia called the Subaru Casa Blanca.

== Motorsports ==
[[Image:Auto Show 069.jpg|thumb|RIGHT|2006 Impreza Rally Car]]
[[Image:Subaru Monte-Carlo 2005.jpg|thumb|right|[[Stéphane Sarrazin]] driving a Subaru Impreza WRC on the [[Monte Carlo Rally]]]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Cusco Dunlop Subaru Impreza.jpg|thumb|right|Cusco Dunlop Subaru Impreza during [[2008 Super GT season]]]] --&gt;

The Impreza chassis has been more successful in [[rallying]] than Subaru's previous contenders. Prior to the introduction of the Impreza into [[World Rally Championship]] racing in 1993, the [[Subaru World Rally Team]] had fielded its larger [[mid-size]] [[Subaru Legacy|Legacy]].  However, with the rest of the rally competition increasingly shifting towards smaller and lighter chassis, Subaru introduced the smaller Impreza, immediately achieving a podium on its debut on the 1993 [[1000 Lakes Rally]]. To jumpstart its early rally efforts, and to develop the Impreza into a competitive rally car, Subaru teamed up with its current preporatory firm, British motorsports company [[Prodrive]], in 1989.

Immediately following the first overall WRC event win for both the fledgling Subaru team and its young driver, the late [[Colin McRae]] aboard a [[Group A]] [[Subaru Legacy|Legacy]] on the [[1993 World Rally Championship season|1993]] [[Rally New Zealand]], the [[Scotland|Scotman]]'s team-mate and childhood idol, [[1981 World Rally Championship season|1981]] [[List of World Rally Championship Drivers' Champions|World Rally Champion]], [[Ari Vatanen]] of [[Finland]], went on to finish second in the debut rally of the first ever factory Impreza. New recruit for the following season, [[1990 World Rally Championship season|1990]] and [[1992 World Rally Championship season|1992]] World Champion, [[Carlos Sainz]] brought the Impreza its inaugural victory on the [[1994 World Rally Championship season|1994]] [[Acropolis Rally]].

The Impreza brought [[Subaru]] three consecutive WRC [[List of World Rally Championship Constructors' Champions|constructors' titles]] ([[1995 World Rally Championship season|1995]]–[[1997 World Rally Championship season|1997]], the latter season the first for the newly introduced [[World Rally Car]] class) and a driver's championship for McRae in 1995, the late [[Richard Burns]] in [[2001 World Rally Championship season|2001]], and the [[Norway|Norwegian]], [[Petter Solberg]] in [[2003 World Rally Championship season|2003]].

Another evolution of the Impreza WRC made its debut in the 2007 [[Corona Rally Mexico]]. Unfortunately, the team had several major problems with reliability as the car experienced mechanical difficulties in almost every rally from its first.

Subaru debuted an Impreza WRC in hatchback form for the first time from the [[2008 World Rally Championship season|2008]] [[Acropolis Rally]] onwards, on which event Solberg scored a second place finish.

On 16 December 2008 Subaru announced that it would withdraw from the [[World Rally Championship]] due to economic problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.swrt.com/news/latest_news.html?id=1590
 |title= Subaru to withdraw from World Rally Championship
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the Subaru Rally Team USA is still competing in the Rally America National Championship. Also, there are still several teams using Subaru models in the Intercontinental Rally Challenge.

== Safety ==
In Australia, the 1993-2004 Subaru Impreza was assessed in the Used Car Safety Ratings 2006 as providing &quot;average&quot; protection for its occupants in the event of a crash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rta.nsw.gov.au/roadsafety/downloads/buyers_guide_used_car_safety_ratings.pdf |title=Buyers Guide to used Car Safety Ratings 2006 |accessdate=2008-02-06 |format=PDF |language=en |work=RTA.nsw.gov.au}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.howsafeisyourcar.com.au/_scripts/ucsr_search_result.php?IID=16999 |title=SAFETY REPORT: SUBARU IMPREZA (1993-2000) |accessdate=2008-02-06 |work=HowSafeIsYourCar.com.au |language=en }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.howsafeisyourcar.com.au/_scripts/ucsr_search_result.php?IID=16910 |title=SAFETY REPORT: SUBARU IMPREZA (2001-2005) |accessdate=2008-02-06 |work=HowSafeIsYourCar.com.au |language=en }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In frontal-offset and side crash tests conducted by the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety in the United States, the second-generation Impreza earned &quot;Good&quot; ratings.  2005-2007 models also earned a &quot;Good&quot; rating for rear crash protection (head restraint design) placing it at the top of IIHS small car ratings.

The third generation MY2008 Impreza continued the tradition and also earned the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety highest rating for &quot;Good&quot; in each individual test, earning an overall score of &quot;Good&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;iihs&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.iihs.org/ratings/ratingsbyseries.aspx?id=349 |title=IIHS-HLDI: Subaru Impreza |accessdate=2008-02-06 |work=IIHS.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The third generation MY2008 Impreza hatchback received five stars (34.66 out of 37 points) for occupant protection and a four star pedestrian rating under testing by ANCAP.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://ancap.com.au/results/232/
 |title= Subaru Impreza: Crash Results
 |work=ANCAP.com.au
 |accessdate=2008-03-30
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Awards and acknowledgments ==
The Impreza was ''[[Wheels magazine|Wheels]]'' magazine's [[Car of the Year]] for 2000.  [[Car and Driver]] Magazine named the North American market WRX to its prestigious [[Car and Driver Ten Best|10-best]] list in 2002, with a follow-up performance in 2003.

== See also ==
* [[Subaru World Rally Team]]

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
&lt;!--========================({{No More Links}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =======================({{No More Links}})=============================--&gt;
*Official Subaru websites: [http://www.subaru.com/ America], [http://www.subaru.co.jp/ Japan], and [http://www.subaru.com.au/ Australia]
*{{dmoz|Recreation/Autos/Makes_and_Models/Subaru/Impreza/|Subaru Impreza}}

{{Subaru}}

[[Category:Subaru vehicles|Impreza]]
[[Category:All wheel drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Front wheel drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Rally cars]]
[[Category:Coupes]]
[[Category:Hatchbacks]]
[[Category:Sedans]]
[[Category:Station wagons]]
[[Category:1990s automobiles]]
[[Category:2000s automobiles]]
[[Category:2010s automobiles]]
[[Category:Vehicles introduced in 1993]]
[[Category:Vehicles with boxer engines]]
[[Category:Motor vehicles manufactured in the United States]]

[[ar:سوبارو إمبريزا]]
[[ca:Subaru Impreza]]
[[cs:Subaru Impreza]]
[[da:Subaru Impreza]]
[[de:Subaru Impreza]]
[[es:Subaru Impreza]]
[[fr:Subaru Impreza]]
[[gl:Subaru Impreza]]
[[ko:스바루 임프레자]]
[[id:Subaru Impreza]]
[[it:Subaru Impreza]]
[[he:סובארו אימפרזה]]
[[hu:Subaru Impreza]]
[[nl:Subaru Impreza]]
[[ja:スバル・インプレッサ]]
[[pl:Subaru Impreza]]
[[pt:Subaru Impreza]]
[[ru:Subaru Impreza]]
[[simple:Impreza]]
[[fi:Subaru Impreza]]
[[sv:Subaru Impreza]]
[[uk:Subaru Impreza]]</text>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
